<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="dyndb-info"><info><title>DynDB (Dynamic Database)</title></info>

  <para>
    DynDB is an extension to BIND 9 which, like DLZ
    (see <xref linkend="dlz-info"/>), allows zone data to be
    retrieved from an external database.  Unlike DLZ, a DynDB module
    provides a full-featured BIND zone database interface.  Where
    DLZ translates DNS queries into real-time database lookups,
    resulting in relatively poor query performance, and is unable
    to handle DNSSEC-signed data due to its limited API, a DynDB
    module can pre-load an in-memory database from the external
    data source, providing the same performance and functionality
    as zones served natively by BIND.
  </para>
  <para>
    A DynDB module supporting LDAP has been created by Red Hat
    and is available from
    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://fedorahosted.org/bind-dyndb-ldap/">https://fedorahosted.org/bind-dyndb-ldap/</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    A sample DynDB module for testing and developer guidance
    is included with the BIND source code, in the directory
    <filename>bin/tests/system/dyndb/driver</filename>.
  </para>

  <section><info><title>Configuring DynDB</title></info>

    <para>
      A DynDB database is configured with a <command>dyndb</command>
      statement in <filename>named.conf</filename>:
    </para>
    <screen>
    dyndb example "driver.so" {
        <replaceable>parameters</replaceable>
    };
    </screen>
    <para>
      The file <filename>driver.so</filename> is a DynDB module which
      implements the full DNS database API.  Multiple
      <command>dyndb</command> statements can be specified, to load
      different drivers or multiple instances of the same driver.
      Zones provided by a DynDB module are added to the view's zone
      table, and are treated as normal authoritative zones when BIND
      is responding to queries.  Zone configuration is handled internally
      by the DynDB module.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <replaceable>parameters</replaceable> are passed as an opaque
      string to the DynDB module's initialization routine. Configuration
      syntax will differ depending on the driver.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section><info><title>Sample DynDB Module</title></info>

    <para>
      For guidance in implementation of DynDB modules, the directory
      <filename>bin/tests/system/dyndb/driver</filename>.
      contains a basic DynDB module.
      The example sets up two zones, whose names are passed
      to the module as arguments in the <command>dyndb</command>
      statement:
    </para>
    <screen>
    dyndb sample "sample.so" { example.nil. arpa. };
    </screen>
    <para>
      In the above example, the module is configured to create a zone
      "example.nil", which can answer queries and AXFR requests, and
      accept DDNS updates.  At runtime, prior to any updates, the zone
      contains an SOA, NS, and a single A record at the apex:
    </para>
    <screen>
 example.nil.  86400    IN      SOA     example.nil. example.nil. (
                                               0 28800 7200 604800 86400
                                       )
 example.nil.  86400    IN      NS      example.nil.
 example.nil.  86400    IN      A       127.0.0.1
    </screen>
    <para>
      When the zone is updated dynamically, the DynDB module will determine
      whether the updated RR is an address (i.e., type A or AAAA) and if
      so, it will automatically update the corresponding PTR record in a
      reverse zone.  (Updates are not stored permanently; all updates are
      lost when the server is restarted.)
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
