<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY scaron "&#x161;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY iacute "&#x0ED;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.14 is a stable branch of BIND.
      This document summarizes significant changes since the last
      production release on that branch.
    <para>
    </para>
      Please see the file <filename>CHANGES</filename> for a more
      detailed list of changes and bug fixes.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_versions"><info><title>Note on Version Numbering</title></info>
    <para>
      As of BIND 9.13/9.14, BIND has adopted the "odd-unstable/even-stable"
      release numbering convention.  BIND 9.14 contains new features added
      during the BIND 9.13 development process. Henceforth, the 9.14 branch
      will be limited to bug fixes and new feature development will proceed
      in the unstable 9.15 branch, and so forth.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_platforms"><info><title>Supported Platforms</title></info>
    <para>
      Since 9.12, BIND has undergone substantial code refactoring and
      cleanup, and some very old code has been removed that was needed
      to support legacy platforms which are no longer supported by their
      vendors and for which ISC is no longer able to perform quality
      assurance testing.  Specifically, workarounds for old versions of
      UnixWare, BSD/OS, AIX, Tru64, SunOS, TruCluster and IRIX have been
      removed.
    </para>
    <para>
      On UNIX-like systems, BIND now requires support for POSIX.1c
      threads (IEEE Std 1003.1c-1995), the Advanced Sockets API for
      IPv6 (RFC 3542), and standard atomic operations provided by the
      C compiler.
    </para>
    <para>
      More information can be found in the <filename>PLATFORM.md</filename>
      file that is included in the source distribution of BIND 9.  If your
      platform compiler and system libraries provide the above features,
      BIND 9 should compile and run. If that isn't the case, the BIND
      development team will generally accept patches that add support
      for systems that are still supported by their respective vendors.
    </para>
    <para>
      As of BIND 9.14, the BIND development team has also made cryptography
      (i.e., TSIG and DNSSEC) an integral part of the DNS server.  The
      OpenSSL cryptography library must be available for the target
      platform.  A PKCS#11 provider can be used instead for Public Key
      cryptography (i.e., DNSSEC signing and validation), but OpenSSL is
      still required for general cryptography operations such as hashing
      and random number generation.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  In certain configurations, <command>named</command> could crash
	  with an assertion failure if <command>nxdomain-redirect</command>
	  was in use and a redirected query resulted in an NXDOMAIN from the
	  cache. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2019-6467. [GL #880]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The TCP client quota set using the <command>tcp-clients</command>
	  option could be exceeded in some cases. This could lead to
	  exhaustion of file descriptors. (CVE-2018-5743) [GL #615]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>add-soa</command> option specifies whether
	  or not the <command>response-policy</command> zone's SOA record
	  should be included in the additional section of RPZ responses.
	  [GL #865]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  None.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>allow-update</command> and
	  <command>allow-update-forwarding</command> options were
	  inadvertently treated as configuration errors when used at the
	  <command>options</command> or <command>view</command> level.
	  This has now been corrected.
	  [GL #913]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND is open source software licenced under the terms of the Mozilla
      Public License, version 2.0 (see the <filename>LICENSE</filename>
      file for the full text).
    </para>
    <para>
      The license requires that if you make changes to BIND and distribute
      them outside your organization, those changes must be published under
      the same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you have made to our software.  This
      requirement does not affect anyone who is using BIND, with or without
      modifications, without redistributing it, nor anyone redistributing
      BIND without changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those wishing to discuss license compliance may contact ISC at
      <link
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
	https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      The end of life date for BIND 9.14 has not yet been determined.
      For those needing long term support, the current Extended Support
      Version (ESV) is BIND 9.11, which will be supported until at
      least December 2021. See
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
      for details of ISC's software support policy.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
