<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The new GeoIP2 API from MaxMind is now supported when BIND
        is compiled using <command>configure --with-geoip2</command>.
        The legacy GeoIP API can be used by compiling with
        <command>configure --with-geoip</command> instead.  (Note that
        the databases for the legacy API are no longer maintained by
        MaxMind.)
      </para>
      <para>
        The default path to the GeoIP2 databases will be set based
        on the location of the <command>libmaxminddb</command> library;
        for example, if it is in <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename>,
        then the default path will be
        <filename>/usr/local/share/GeoIP</filename>.
        This value can be overridden in <filename>named.conf</filename>
        using the <command>geoip-directory</command> option.
      </para>
      <para>
        Some <command>geoip</command> ACL settings that were available with
        legacy GeoIP, including searches for <command>netspeed</command>,
        <command>org</command>, and three-letter ISO country codes, will
        no longer work when using GeoIP2. Supported GeoIP2 database
        types are <command>country</command>, <command>city</command>,
        <command>domain</command>, <command>isp</command>, and
        <command>as</command>. All of the databases support both IPv4
        and IPv6 lookups. [GL #182]
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Two new metrics have been added to the
        <command>statistics-channel</command> to report DNSSEC
        signing operations.  For each key in each zone, the
        <command>dnssec-sign</command> counter indicates the total
        number of signatures <command>named</command> has generated
        using that key since server startup, and the
        <command>dnssec-refresh</command> counter indicates how
        many of those signatures were refreshed during zone
        maintenance, as opposed to having been generated
        as a result of a zone update.  [GL #513]
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A SipHash 2-4 based DNS Cookie (RFC 7873) algorithm has been added.
        [GL #605]
      </para>
      <para>
        If you are running multiple DNS Servers (different versions of BIND 9
        or DNS server from multiple vendors) responding from the same IP
        address (anycast or load-balancing scenarios), you'll have to make
        sure that all the servers are configured with the same DNS Cookie
        algorithm and same Server Secret for the best performance.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        DS records included in DNS referral messages can now be validated
        and cached immediately, reducing the number of queries needed for
        a DNSSEC validation. [GL #964]
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
