<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xml:id="relnotes-9.14.0"><info><title>Notes for BIND 9.14.0</title></info>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.14.0-features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Task manager and socket code have been substantially modified.
          The manager uses per-cpu queues for tasks and network stack runs
          multiple event loops in CPU-affinitive threads. This greatly
          improves performance on large systems, especially when using
          multi-queue NICs.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for QNAME minimization was added and enabled by default
          in <command>relaxed</command> mode, in which BIND will fall back
          to normal resolution if the remote server returns something
          unexpected during the query minimization process. This default
          setting might change to <command>strict</command> in the future.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A new <command>plugin</command> mechanism has been added to allow
          extension of query processing functionality through the use of
          external libraries. The new <filename>filter-aaaa.so</filename>
          plugin replaces the <command>filter-aaaa</command> feature that
          was formerly implemented as a native part of BIND.
        </para>
        <para>
          The plugin API is a work in progress and is likely to evolve
          as further plugins are implemented. [GL #15]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A new secondary zone option, <command>mirror</command>,
          enables <command>named</command> to serve a transferred copy
          of a zone's contents without acting as an authority for the
          zone. A zone must be fully validated against an active trust
          anchor before it can be used as a mirror zone. DNS responses
          from mirror zones do not set the AA bit ("authoritative answer"),
          but do set the AD bit ("authenticated data"). This feature is
          meant to facilitate deployment of a local copy of the root zone,
          as described in RFC 7706. [GL #33]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          BIND now can be compiled against the <command>libidn2</command>
          library to add IDNA2008 support.  Previously, BIND supported
          IDNA2003 using the (now obsolete and unsupported)
          <command>idnkit-1</command> library.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> now supports the "root key sentinel"
          mechanism. This enables validating resolvers to indicate
          which trust anchors are configured for the root, so that
          information about root key rollover status can be gathered.
          To disable this feature, add
          <command>root-key-sentinel no;</command> to
          <filename>named.conf</filename>. [GL #37]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>dnskey-sig-validity</command> option allows the
          <command>sig-validity-interval</command> to be overriden for
          signatures covering DNSKEY RRsets. [GL #145]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When built on Linux, BIND now requires the <command>libcap</command>
          library to set process privileges.  The adds a new compile-time
          dependency, which can be met on most Linux platforms by installing the
          <command>libcap-dev</command> or <command>libcap-devel</command>
          package. BIND can also be built without capability support by using
          <command>configure --disable-linux-caps</command>, at the cost of some
          loss of security.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>validate-except</command> option specifies a list of
          domains beneath which DNSSEC validation should not be performed,
          regardless of whether a trust anchor has been configured above
          them. [GL #237]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Two new update policy rule types have been added
          <command>krb5-selfsub</command> and <command>ms-selfsub</command>
          which allow machines with Kerberos principals to update
          the name space at or below the machine names identified
          in the respective principals.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The new configure option <command>--enable-fips-mode</command>
          can be used to make BIND enable and enforce FIPS mode in the
          OpenSSL library.  When compiled with such option the BIND will
          refuse to run if FIPS mode can't be enabled, thus this option
          must be only enabled for the systems where FIPS mode is available.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Two new configuration options <command>min-cache-ttl</command> and
          <command>min-ncache-ttl</command> has been added to allow the BIND 9
          administrator to override the minimum TTL in the received DNS records
          (positive caching) and for storing the information about non-existent
          records (negative caching).  The configured minimum TTL for both
          configuration options cannot exceed 90 seconds.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>rndc status</command> output now includes a
          <command>reconfig/reload in progress</command> status line if named
          configuration is being reloaded.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The new <command>answer-cookie</command> option, if set to
          <literal>no</literal>, prevents <command>named</command> from
          returning a DNS COOKIE option to a client, even if such an
          option was present in the request.  This is only intended as
          a temporary measure, for use when <command>named</command>
          shares an IP address with other servers that do not yet
          support DNS COOKIE.  A mismatch between servers on the same
          address is not expected to cause operational problems, but the
          option to disable COOKIE responses so that all servers have the
          same behavior is provided out of an abundance of caution.
          DNS COOKIE is an important security mechanism, and this option
          should not be used to disable it unless absolutely necessary.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.14.0-removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Workarounds for servers that misbehave when queried with EDNS
          have been removed, because these broken servers and the
          workarounds for their noncompliance cause unnecessary delays,
          increase code complexity, and prevent deployment of new DNS
          features. See <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
            xlink:href="https://dnsflagday.net">https://dnsflagday.net</link>
          for further details.
        </para>
        <para>
          In particular, resolution will no longer fall back to
          plain DNS when there was no response from an authoritative
          server.  This will cause some domains to become non-resolvable
          without manual intervention.  In these cases, resolution can
          be restored by adding <command>server</command> clauses for the
          offending servers, specifying <command>edns no</command> or
          <command>send-cookie no</command>, depending on the specific
          noncompliance.
        </para>
        <para>
          To determine which <command>server</command> clause to use, run
          the following commands to send queries to the authoritative
          servers for the broken domain:
        </para>
<literallayout>
          dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +dnssec
          dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +dnssec +nocookie
          dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +noedns
</literallayout>
        <para>
          If the first command fails but the second succeeds, the
          server most likely needs <command>send-cookie no</command>.
          If the first two fail but the third succeeds, then the server
          needs EDNS to be fully disabled with <command>edns no</command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Please contact the administrators of noncompliant domains
          and encourage them to upgrade their broken DNS servers. [GL #150]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Previously, it was possible to build BIND without thread support
          for old architectures and systems without threads support.
          BIND now requires threading support (either POSIX or Windows) from
          the operating system, and it cannot be built without threads.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>filter-aaaa</command>,
          <command>filter-aaaa-on-v4</command>, and
          <command>filter-aaaa-on-v6</command> options have been removed
          from <command>named</command>, and can no longer be
          configured using native <filename>named.conf</filename> syntax.
          However, loading the new <filename>filter-aaaa.so</filename>
          plugin and setting its parameters provides identical
          functionality.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> can no longer use the EDNS CLIENT-SUBNET
          option for view selection.  In its existing form, the authoritative
          ECS feature was not fully RFC-compliant, and could not realistically
          have been deployed in production for an authoritative server; its
          only practical use was for testing and experimentation. In the
          interest of code simplification, this feature has now been removed.
        </para>
        <para>
          The ECS option is still supported in <command>dig</command> and
          <command>mdig</command> via the +subnet argument, and can be parsed
          and logged when received by <command>named</command>, but
          it is no longer used for ACL processing. The
          <command>geoip-use-ecs</command> option is now obsolete;
          a warning will be logged if it is used in
          <filename>named.conf</filename>.
          <command>ecs</command> tags in an ACL definition are
          also obsolete, and will cause the configuration to fail to
          load if they are used. [GL #32]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>dnssec-keygen</command> can no longer generate HMAC
          keys for TSIG authentication. Use <command>tsig-keygen</command>
          to generate these keys. [RT #46404]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for OpenSSL 0.9.x has been removed.  OpenSSL version
          1.0.0 or greater, or LibreSSL is now required.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>configure --enable-seccomp</command> option,
          which formerly turned on system-call filtering on Linux, has
          been removed. [GL #93]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          IPv4 addresses in forms other than dotted-quad are no longer
          accepted in master files. [GL #13] [GL #56]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          IDNA2003 support via (bundled) idnkit-1.0 has been removed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The "rbtdb64" database implementation (a parallel
          implementation of "rbt") has been removed. [GL #217]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>-r randomdev</command> option to explicitly select
          random device has been removed from the
          <command>ddns-confgen</command>,
          <command>rndc-confgen</command>,
          <command>nsupdate</command>,
          <command>dnssec-confgen</command>, and
          <command>dnssec-signzone</command> commands.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <command>-p</command> option to use pseudo-random data
          has been removed from the <command>dnssec-signzone</command>
          command.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for the RSAMD5 algorithm has been removed freom BIND as
          the usage of the RSAMD5 algorithm for DNSSEC has been deprecated
          in RFC6725, the security of the MD5 algorithm has been compromised,
          and its usage is considered harmful.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for the ECC-GOST (GOST R 34.11-94) algorithm has been
          removed from BIND, as the algorithm has been superseded by
          GOST R 34.11-2012 in RFC6986 and it must not be used in new
          deployments.  BIND will neither create new DNSSEC keys,
          signatures and digests, nor it will validate them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for DSA and DSA-NSEC3-SHA1 algorithms has been
          removed from BIND as the DSA key length is limited to 1024
          bits and this is not considered secure enough.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> will no longer ignore "no-change" deltas
          when processing an IXFR stream.  This had previously been
          permitted for compatibility with BIND 8, but now "no-change"
          deltas will trigger a fallback to AXFR as the recovery mechanism.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          BIND 9 will no longer build on platforms that don't have
          proper IPv6 support.  BIND 9 now also requires POSIX-compatible
          pthread support.  Most of the platforms that lack these featuers
          are long past their end-of-lifew dates, and they are neither
          developed nor supported by their respective vendors.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The incomplete support for internationalization message catalogs has
          been removed from BIND. Since the internationalization was never
          completed, and no localized message catalogs were ever made available
          for the portions of BIND in which they could have been used, this
          change will have no effect except to simplify the source code. BIND's
          log messages and other output were already only available in English.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.14.0-changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          BIND will now always use the best CSPRNG (cryptographically-secure
          pseudo-random number generator) available on the platform where
          it is compiled.  It will use the <command>arc4random()</command>
          family of functions on BSD operating systems,
          <command>getrandom()</command> on Linux and Solaris,
          <command>CryptGenRandom</command> on Windows, and the selected
          cryptography provider library (OpenSSL or PKCS#11) as the last
          resort. [GL #221]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The default setting for <command>dnssec-validation</command> is
          now <userinput>auto</userinput>, which activates DNSSEC
          validation using the IANA root key. (The default can be changed
          back to <userinput>yes</userinput>, which activates DNSSEC
          validation only when keys are explicitly configured in
          <filename>named.conf</filename>, by building BIND with
          <command>configure --disable-auto-validation</command>.) [GL #30]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          BIND can no longer be built without DNSSEC support. A cryptography
          provider (i.e., OpenSSL or a hardware service module with
          PKCS#11 support) must be available. [GL #244]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Zone types <command>primary</command> and
          <command>secondary</command> are now available as synonyms for
          <command>master</command> and <command>slave</command>,
          respectively, in <filename>named.conf</filename>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> will now log a warning if the old
          root DNSSEC key is explicitly configured and has not been updated.
          [RT #43670]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>dig +nssearch</command> will now list name servers
          that have timed out, in addition to those that respond. [GL #64]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Up to 64 <command>response-policy</command> zones are now
          supported by default; previously the limit was 32. [GL #123]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Several configuration options for time periods can now use
          TTL value suffixes (for example, <literal>2h</literal> or
          <literal>1d</literal>) in addition to an integer number of
          seconds. These include
          <command>fstrm-set-reopen-interval</command>,
          <command>interface-interval</command>,
          <command>max-cache-ttl</command>,
          <command>max-ncache-ttl</command>,
          <command>max-policy-ttl</command>, and
          <command>min-update-interval</command>.
          [GL #203]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          NSID logging (enabled by the <command>request-nsid</command>
          option) now has its own <command>nsid</command> category,
          instead of using the <command>resolver</command> category.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <command>rndc nta</command> command could not differentiate
          between views of the same name but different class; this
          has been corrected with the addition of a <command>-class</command>
          option. [GL #105]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>allow-recursion-on</command> and
          <command>allow-query-cache-on</command> each now default to
          the other if only one of them is set, in order to be consistent
          with the way <command>allow-recursion</command> and
          <command>allow-query-cache</command> work. [GL #319]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When compiled with IDN support, the <command>dig</command> and
          <command>nslookup</command> commands now disable IDN processing
          when the standard output is not a TTY (i.e., when the output
          is not being read by a human). When running from a shell
          script, the command line options <command>+idnin</command> and
          <command>+idnout</command> may be used to enable IDN
          processing of input and output domain names, respectively.
          When running on a TTY, the <command>+noidnin</command> and
          <command>+noidnout</command> options may be used to disable
          IDN processing of input and output domain names.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The configuration option <command>max-ncache-ttl</command> cannot
          exceed seven days. Previously, larger values than this were silently
          lowered; now, they trigger a configuration error.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The new <command>dig -r</command> command line option
          disables reading of the file <filename>$HOME/.digrc</filename>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Zone signing and key maintenance events are now logged to the
          <command>dnssec</command> category rather than
          <command>zone</command>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</section>
