<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY scaron "&#x161;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY iacute "&#x0ED;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      This document summarizes changes since the last production
      release on the BIND 9.12 branch. Please see the
      <filename>CHANGES</filename> for a further list of bug fixes
      and other changes.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> could crash during recursive processing
	  of DNAME records when <command>deny-answer-aliases</command> was
	  in use. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5740. [GL #387]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When recursion is enabled but the <command>allow-recursion</command>
	  and <command>allow-query-cache</command> ACLs are not specified, they
	  should be limited to local networks, but they were inadvertently set
	  to match the default <command>allow-query</command>, thus allowing
	  remote queries. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5738. [GL #309]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The serve-stale feature could cause an assertion failure in
	  rbtdb.c even when stale-answer-enable was false. The
	  simultaneous use of stale cache records and NSEC aggressive
	  negative caching could trigger a recursion loop in the
	  <command>named</command> process. This flaw is disclosed in
	  CVE-2018-5737. [GL #185]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A bug in zone database reference counting could lead to a crash
	  when multiple versions of a slave zone were transferred from a
	  master in close succession. This flaw is disclosed in
	  CVE-2018-5736. [GL #134]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>update-policy</command> rules that otherwise ignore the
	  name field now require that it be set to "." to ensure that any
	  type list present is properly interpreted.  Previously, if the
	  name field was omitted from the rule declaration but a type list
	  was present, it wouldn't be interpreted as expected.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now supports the "root key sentinel"
	  mechanism. This enables validating resolvers to indicate
	  which trust anchors are configured for the root, so that
	  information about root key rollover status can be gathered.
	  To disable this feature, add
	  <command>root-key-sentinel no;</command> to
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [GL #37]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Add the ability to not return a DNS COOKIE option when one
	  is present in the request.  To prevent a cookie being returned
	  add <command>answer-cookie no;</command> to
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [GL #173]
	</para>
	<para>
	  <command>answer-cookie no</command> is only intended as a
	  temporary measure, for use when <command>named</command>
	  shares an IP address with other servers that do not yet
	  support DNS COOKIE.  A mismatch between servers on the
	  same address is not expected to cause operational problems,
	  but the option to disable COOKIE responses so that all
	  servers have the same behavior is provided out of an
	  abundance of caution. DNS COOKIE is an important security
	  mechanism, and should not be disabled unless absolutely
	  necessary.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BIND now can be compiled against libidn2 library to add
	  IDNA2008 support.  Previously BIND only supported IDNA2003
	  using (now obsolete) idnkit-1 library.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +noidnin</command> can be used to disable IDN
	  processing on the input domain name, when BIND is compiled
	  with IDN support.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now rejects excessively large
	  incremental (IXFR) zone transfers in order to prevent
	  possible corruption of journal files which could cause
	  <command>named</command> to abort when loading zones. [GL #339]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND is open source software licenced under the terms of the Mozilla
      Public License, version 2.0 (see the <filename>LICENSE</filename>
      file for the full text).
    </para>
    <para>
      The license requires that if you make changes to BIND and distribute
      them outside your organization, those changes must be published under
      the same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you have made to our software.  This
      requirement does not affect anyone who is using BIND, with or without
      modifications, without redistributing it, nor anyone redistributing
      BIND without changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those wishing to discuss license compliance may contact ISC at
      <link
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
	https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      The end-of-life date for BIND 9.12 has not yet been determined.
      However, it is not intended to be an Extended Support Version (ESV)
      branch; accordingly, support will end after the next stable
      branch (9.14) becomes available.  Those needing a longer-lived
      branch are encouraged to use the current ESV, BIND 9.11, which
      will be supported until December 2021. See
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
      for details of ISC's software support policy.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
