<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xml:id="relnotes_platforms"><info><title>Supported Platforms</title></info>
  <para>
    Since 9.12, BIND has undergone substantial code refactoring and
    cleanup, and some very old code has been removed that supported
    obsolete operating systems and operating systems for which ISC is
    no longer able to perform quality assurance testing. Specifically,
    workarounds for UnixWare, BSD/OS, AIX, Tru64, SunOS, TruCluster
    and IRIX have been removed.
  </para>
  <para>
    On UNIX-like systems, BIND now requires support for POSIX.1c
    threads (IEEE Std 1003.1c-1995), the Advanced Sockets API for
    IPv6 (RFC 3542), and standard atomic operations provided by the
    C compiler.
  </para>
  <para>
    More information can be found in the <filename>PLATFORM.md</filename>
    file that is included in the source distribution of BIND 9.  If your
    platform compiler and system libraries provide the above features,
    BIND 9 should compile and run. If that isn't the case, the BIND
    development team will generally accept patches that add support
    for systems that are still supported by their respective vendors.
  </para>
  <para>
    As of BIND 9.14, the BIND development team has also made cryptography
    (i.e., TSIG and DNSSEC) an integral part of the DNS server.  The
    OpenSSL cryptography library must be available for the target
    platform.  A PKCS#11 provider can be used instead for Public Key
    cryptography (i.e., DNSSEC signing and validation), but OpenSSL is
    still required for general cryptography operations such as hashing
    and random number generation.
  </para>
</section>
