<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY scaron "&#x161;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY iacute "&#x0ED;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.13 is an unstable development release of BIND.
      This document summarizes new features and functional changes that
      have been introduced on this branch.  With each development release
      leading up to the stable BIND 9.14 release, this document will be
      updated with additional features added and bugs fixed.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_versions"><info><title>Note on Version Numbering</title></info>
    <para>
      Prior to BIND 9.13, new feature development releases were tagged
      as "alpha" and "beta", leading up to the first stable release
      for a given development branch, which always ended in ".0".
    </para>
    <para>
      Now, however, BIND has adopted the "odd-unstable/even-stable"
      release numbering convention. There will be no "alpha" or "beta"
      releases in the 9.13 branch, only increasing version numbers.
      So, for example, what would previously have been called 9.13.0a1,
      9.13.0a2, 9.13.0b1, and so on, will instead be called 9.13.0,
      9.13.1, 9.13.2, etc.
    </para>
    <para>
      The first stable release from this development branch will be
      renamed as 9.14.0. Thereafter, maintenance releases will continue
      on the 9.14 branch, while unstable feature development proceeds in
      9.15.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_platforms"><info><title>Supported Platforms</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.13 has undergone substantial code refactoring and cleanup,
      and some very old code has been removed that was needed to support
      legacy platforms which are no longer supported by their vendors
      and for which ISC is no longer able to perform quality assurance
      testing.  Specifically, workarounds for old versions of UnixWare,
      BSD/OS, AIX, Tru64, SunOS, TruCluster and IRIX have been removed.
      On UNIX-like systems, BIND now requires support for POSIX.1c
      threads (IEEE Std 1003.1c-1995), the Advanced Sockets API for
      IPv6 (RFC 3542), and standard atomic operations provided by the
      C compiler.
    </para>
    <para>
      More information can be found in the <filename>PLATFORM.md</filename>
      file that is included in the source distribution of BIND 9.  If your
      platform compiler and system libraries provide the above features,
      BIND 9 should compile and run. If that isn't the case, the BIND
      development team will generally accept patches that add support
      for systems that are still supported by their respective vendors.
    </para>
    <para>
      As of BIND 9.13, the BIND development team has also made cryptography
      (i.e., TSIG and DNSSEC) an integral part of the DNS server.  The
      OpenSSL cryptography library must be available for the target
      platform.  A PKCS#11 provider can be used instead for Public Key
      cryptography (i.e., DNSSEC signing and validation), but OpenSSL is
      still required for general cryptography operations such as hashing
      and random number generation.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There was a long-existing flaw in the documentation for
          <command>ms-self</command>, <command>krb5-self</command>,
          <command>ms-subdomain</command>, and <command>krb5-subdomain</command>
          rules in <command>update-policy</command> statements.  Though
          the policies worked as intended, operators who configured their
          servers according to the misleading documentation may have
          thought zone updates were more restricted than they were;
          users of these rule types are advised to review the documentation
          and correct their configurations if necessary.  New rule types
          matching the previously documented behavior will be introduced
          in a future maintenance release. [GL !708]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When recursion is enabled but the <command>allow-recursion</command>
	  and <command>allow-query-cache</command> ACLs are not specified, they
	  should be limited to local networks, but they were inadvertently set
	  to match the default <command>allow-query</command>, thus allowing
	  remote queries. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5738. [GL #309]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> could crash during recursive processing
	  of DNAME records when <command>deny-answer-aliases</command> was
	  in use. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5740. [GL #387]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Code change #4964, intended to prevent double signatures
	  when deleting an inactive zone DNSKEY in some situations,
	  introduced a new problem during zone processing in which
	  some delegation glue RRsets are incorrectly identified
	  as needing RRSIGs, which are then created for them using
	  the current active ZSK for the zone. In some, but not all
	  cases, the newly-signed RRsets are added to the zone's
	  NSEC/NSEC3 chain, but incompletely -- this can result in
	  a broken chain, affecting validation of proof of nonexistence
	  for records in the zone. [GL #771]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> could crash if it managed a DNSSEC
	  security root with <command>managed-keys</command> and the
	  authoritative zone rolled the key to an algorithm not supported
	  by BIND 9.  This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5745. [GL #780]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> leaked memory when processing a
	  request with multiple Key Tag EDNS options present. ISC
	  would like to thank Toshifumi Sakaguchi for bringing this
	  to our attention.  This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5744.
	  [GL #772]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Zone transfer controls for writable DLZ zones were not
	  effective as the <command>allowzonexfr</command> method was
	  not being called for such zones. This flaw is disclosed in
	  CVE-2019-6465. [GL #790]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Task manager and socket code have been substantially modified.
	  The manager uses per-cpu queues for tasks and network stack runs
	  multiple event loops in CPU-affinitive threads. This greatly
	  improves performance on large systems, especially when using
	  multi-queue NICs.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A new secondary zone option, <command>mirror</command>,
	  enables <command>named</command> to serve a transferred copy
	  of a zone's contents without acting as an authority for the
	  zone. A zone must be fully validated against an active trust
	  anchor before it can be used as a mirror zone. DNS responses
	  from mirror zones do not set the AA bit ("authoritative answer"),
	  but do set the AD bit ("authenticated data"). This feature is
	  meant to facilitate deployment of a local copy of the root zone,
	  as described in RFC 7706. [GL #33]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A new <command>plugin</command> mechanism has been added to allow
	  extension of query processing functionality through the use of
	  external libraries. The new <filename>filter-aaaa.so</filename>
	  plugin replaces the <command>filter-aaaa</command> feature that
	  was formerly implemented as a native part of BIND.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The plugin API is a work in progress and is likely to evolve
	  as further plugins are implemented. [GL #15]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BIND now can be compiled against the <command>libidn2</command>
	  library to add IDNA2008 support.  Previously, BIND supported
	  IDNA2003 using the (now obsolete and unsupported)
	  <command>idnkit-1</command> library.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now supports the "root key sentinel"
	  mechanism. This enables validating resolvers to indicate
	  which trust anchors are configured for the root, so that
	  information about root key rollover status can be gathered.
	  To disable this feature, add
	  <command>root-key-sentinel no;</command> to
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [GL #37]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>dnskey-sig-validity</command> option allows the
	  <command>sig-validity-interval</command> to be overriden for
	  signatures covering DNSKEY RRsets. [GL #145]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Support for QNAME minimization was added and enabled by default
	  in <command>relaxed</command> mode, in which BIND will fall back
	  to normal resolution if the remote server returns something
	  unexpected during the query minimization process. This default
	  setting might change to <command>strict</command> in the future.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When built on Linux, BIND now requires the <command>libcap</command>
	  library to set process privileges.  The adds a new compile-time
	  dependency, which can be met on most Linux platforms by installing the
	  <command>libcap-dev</command> or <command>libcap-devel</command>
	  package. BIND can also be built without capability support by using
	  <command>configure --disable-linux-caps</command>, at the cost of some
	  loss of security.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>validate-except</command> option specifies a list of
	  domains beneath which DNSSEC validation should not be performed,
	  regardless of whether a trust anchor has been configured above
	  them. [GL #237]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Two new update policy rule types have been added
	  <command>krb5-selfsub</command> and <command>ms-selfsub</command>
	  which allow machines with Kerberos principals to update
	  the name space at or below the machine names identified
	  in the respective principals.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new configure option <command>--enable-fips-mode</command>
	  can be used to make BIND enable and enforce FIPS mode in the
	  OpenSSL library.  When compiled with such option the BIND will
	  refuse to run if FIPS mode can't be enabled, thus this option
	  must be only enabled for the systems where FIPS mode is available.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Two new configuration options <command>min-cache-ttl</command> and
	  <command>min-ncache-ttl</command> has been added to allow the BIND 9
	  administrator to override the minimum TTL in the received DNS records
	  (positive caching) and for storing the information about non-existent
	  records (negative caching).  The configured minimum TTL for both
	  configuration options cannot exceed 90 seconds.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>rndc status</command> output now includes a
          <command>reconfig/reload in progress</command> status line if named
          configuration is being reloaded.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Workarounds for servers that misbehave when queried with EDNS
	  have been removed, because these broken servers and the
	  workarounds for their noncompliance cause unnecessary delays,
	  increase code complexity, and prevent deployment of new DNS
	  features. See <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	    xlink:href="https://dnsflagday.net">https://dnsflagday.net</link>
	  for further details.
	</para>
	<para>
	  In particular, resolution will no longer fall back to
	  plain DNS when there was no response from an authoritative
	  server.  This will cause some domains to become non-resolvable
	  without manual intervention.  In these cases, resolution can
	  be restored by adding <command>server</command> clauses for the
	  offending servers, specifying <command>edns no</command> or
	  <command>send-cookie no</command>, depending on the specific
	  noncompliance.
	</para>
	<para>
	  To determine which <command>server</command> clause to use, run
	  the following commands to send queries to the authoritative
	  servers for the broken domain:
	</para>
<literallayout>
	  dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +dnssec
	  dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +dnssec +nocookie
	  dig soa &lt;zone&gt; @&lt;server&gt; +noedns
</literallayout>
	<para>
	  If the first command fails but the second succeeds, the
	  server most likely needs <command>send-cookie no</command>.
	  If the first two fail but the third succeeds, then the server
	  needs EDNS to be fully disabled with <command>edns no</command>.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Please contact the administrators of noncompliant domains
	  and encourage them to upgrade their broken DNS servers. [GL #150]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Previously, it was possible to build BIND without thread support
	  for old architectures and systems without threads support.
	  BIND now requires threading support (either POSIX or Windows) from
	  the operating system, and it cannot be built without threads.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>filter-aaaa</command>,
	  <command>filter-aaaa-on-v4</command>, and
	  <command>filter-aaaa-on-v6</command> options have been removed
	  from <command>named</command>, and can no longer be
	  configured using native <filename>named.conf</filename> syntax.
	  However, loading the new <filename>filter-aaaa.so</filename>
	  plugin and setting its parameters provides identical
	  functionality.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> can no longer use the EDNS CLIENT-SUBNET
	  option for view selection.  In its existing form, the authoritative
	  ECS feature was not fully RFC-compliant, and could not realistically
	  have been deployed in production for an authoritative server; its
	  only practical use was for testing and experimentation. In the
	  interest of code simplification, this feature has now been removed.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The ECS option is still supported in <command>dig</command> and
	  <command>mdig</command> via the +subnet argument, and can be parsed
	  and logged when received by <command>named</command>, but
	  it is no longer used for ACL processing. The
	  <command>geoip-use-ecs</command> option is now obsolete;
	  a warning will be logged if it is used in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>.
	  <command>ecs</command> tags in an ACL definition are
	  also obsolete, and will cause the configuration to fail to
	  load if they are used. [GL #32]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dnssec-keygen</command> can no longer generate HMAC
	  keys for TSIG authentication. Use <command>tsig-keygen</command>
	  to generate these keys. [RT #46404]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Support for OpenSSL 0.9.x has been removed.  OpenSSL version
	  1.0.0 or greater, or LibreSSL is now required.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>configure --enable-seccomp</command> option,
	  which formerly turned on system-call filtering on Linux, has
	  been removed. [GL #93]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  IPv4 addresses in forms other than dotted-quad are no longer
	  accepted in master files. [GL #13] [GL #56]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  IDNA2003 support via (bundled) idnkit-1.0 has been removed.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The "rbtdb64" database implementation (a parallel
	  implementation of "rbt") has been removed. [GL #217]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>-r randomdev</command> option to explicitly select
	  random device has been removed from the
	  <command>ddns-confgen</command>,
	  <command>rndc-confgen</command>,
	  <command>nsupdate</command>,
	  <command>dnssec-confgen</command>, and
	  <command>dnssec-signzone</command> commands.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The <command>-p</command> option to use pseudo-random data
	  has been removed from the <command>dnssec-signzone</command>
	  command.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Support for ECC-GOST (GOST R 34.11-94) algorithm has been
	  removed from BIND as the algorithm has been superseded by
	  GOST R 34.11-2012 in RFC6986 and it must not be used in new
	  deployments.  BIND will neither create new DNSSEC keys,
	  signatures and digest, nor it will validate them.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Add the ability to not return a DNS COOKIE option when one
	  is present in the request.  To prevent a cookie being returned
	  add 'answer-cookie no;' to named.conf. [GL #173]
	</para>
	<para>
	  <command>answer-cookie</command> is only intended as a temporary
	  measure, for use when <command>named</command> shares an IP address
	  with other servers that do not yet support DNS COOKIE.  A mismatch
	  between servers on the same address is not expected to cause
	  operational problems, but the option to disable COOKIE responses so
	  that all servers have the same behavior is provided out of an
	  abundance of caution. DNS COOKIE is an important security mechanism,
	  and should not be disabled unless absolutely necessary.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Remove support for silently ignoring 'no-change' deltas from
	  BIND 8 when processing an IXFR stream.  'no-change' deltas
	  will now trigger a fallback to AXFR as the recovery mechanism.
	</para>
	<para>
	  BIND 9 will no longer build on platforms that doesn't have
	  proper IPv6 support.  BIND 9 now also requires non-broken
	  POSIX-compatible pthread support.  Such platforms are
	  usually long after their end-of-life date and they are
	  neither developed nor supported by their respective vendors.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Support for DSA and DSA-NSEC3-SHA1 algorithms has been
	  removed from BIND as the DSA key length is limited to 1024
	  bits and this is not considered secure enough.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Support for RSAMD5 algorithm has been removed freom BIND as the usage
	  of the RSAMD5 algorithm for DNSSEC has been deprecated in RFC6725 and
	  the security of MD5 algorithm has been compromised and the its usage
	  is considered harmful.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The incomplete support for internationalization message catalogs has
	  been removed from BIND. Since the internationalization was never
	  completed, and no localized message catalogs were ever made available
	  for the portions of BIND in which they could have been used, this
	  change will have no effect except to simplify the source code. BIND's
	  log messages and other output were already only available in English.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BIND will now always use the best CSPRNG (cryptographically-secure
	  pseudo-random number generator) available on the platform where
	  it is compiled.  It will use <command>arc4random()</command>
	  family of functions on BSD operating systems,
	  <command>getrandom()</command> on Linux and Solaris,
	  <command>CryptGenRandom</command> on Windows, and the selected
	  cryptography provider library (OpenSSL or PKCS#11) as the last
	  resort. [GL #221]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The default setting for <command>dnssec-validation</command> is
	  now <userinput>auto</userinput>, which activates DNSSEC
	  validation using the IANA root key. (The default can be changed
	  back to <userinput>yes</userinput>, which activates DNSSEC
	  validation only when keys are explicitly configured in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>, by building BIND with
	  <command>configure --disable-auto-validation</command>.) [GL #30]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BIND can no longer be built without DNSSEC support. A cryptography
	  provider (i.e., OpenSSL or a hardware service module with
	  PKCS#11 support) must be available. [GL #244]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Zone types <command>primary</command> and
	  <command>secondary</command> are now available as synonyms for
	  <command>master</command> and <command>slave</command>,
	  respectively, in <filename>named.conf</filename>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> will now log a warning if the old
	  root DNSSEC key is explicitly configured and has not been updated.
	  [RT #43670]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +nssearch</command> will now list name servers
	  that have timed out, in addition to those that respond. [GL #64]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Up to 64 <command>response-policy</command> zones are now
	  supported by default; previously the limit was 32. [GL #123]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Several configuration options for time periods can now use
	  TTL value suffixes (for example, <literal>2h</literal> or
	  <literal>1d</literal>) in addition to an integer number of
	  seconds. These include
	  <command>fstrm-set-reopen-interval</command>,
	  <command>interface-interval</command>,
	  <command>max-cache-ttl</command>,
	  <command>max-ncache-ttl</command>,
	  <command>max-policy-ttl</command>, and
	  <command>min-update-interval</command>.
	  [GL #203]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  NSID logging (enabled by the <command>request-nsid</command>
	  option) now has its own <command>nsid</command> category,
	  instead of using the <command>resolver</command> category.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>rndc nta</command> command could not differentiate
	  between views of the same name but different class; this
	  has been corrected with the addition of a <command>-class</command>
	  option. [GL #105]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>allow-recursion-on</command> and
	  <command>allow-query-cache-on</command> each now default to
	  the other if only one of them is set, in order to be consistent
	  with the way <command>allow-recursion</command> and
	  <command>allow-query-cache</command> work. [GL #319]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When compiled with IDN support, the <command>dig</command> and
	  <command>nslookup</command> commands now disable IDN processing
	  when the standard output is not a TTY (i.e., when the output
	  is not being read by a human). When running from a shell
	  script, the command line options <command>+idnin</command> and
	  <command>+idnout</command> may be used to enable IDN
	  processing of input and output domain names, respectively.
	  When running on a TTY, the <command>+noidnin</command> and
	  <command>+noidnout</command> options may be used to disable
	  IDN processing of input and output domain names.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The configuration option <command>max-ncache-ttl</command> cannot
	  exceed seven days. Previously, larger values than this were silently
	  lowered; now, they trigger a configuration error.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>dig -r</command> command line option
	  disables reading of the file <filename>$HOME/.digrc</filename>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Zone signing and key maintenance events are now logged to the
	  <command>dnssec</command> category rather than
	  <command>zone</command>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Running <command>rndc reconfig</command> could cause
          <command>inline-signing</command> zones to stop signing.
	  [GL #439]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Reloading all zones caused zone maintenance to stop for
          <command>inline-signing</command> zones. [GL #435]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Signatures loaded from the journal for the signed version
          of an <command>inline-signing</command> zone were not scheduled
	  for refresh. [GL #482]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A referral response with a non-empty ANSWER section was
          incorrectly treated as an error; this caused certain domains
          to be non-resolvable. [GL #390]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When a negative trust anchor was added to multiple views
	  using <command>rndc nta</command>, the text returned via
	  <command>rndc</command> was incorrectly truncated after the
	  first line, making it appear that only one NTA had been
	  added. This has been fixed. [GL #105]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The view name is now included in the output of
	  <command>rndc nta -dump</command>, for consistency with
	  other options. [GL !816]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now rejects excessively large
	  incremental (IXFR) zone transfers in order to prevent
	  possible corruption of journal files which could cause
	  <command>named</command> to abort when loading zones. [GL #339]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND is open source software licenced under the terms of the Mozilla
      Public License, version 2.0 (see the <filename>LICENSE</filename>
      file for the full text).
    </para>
    <para>
      The license requires that if you make changes to BIND and distribute
      them outside your organization, those changes must be published under
      the same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you have made to our software.  This
      requirement does not affect anyone who is using BIND, with or without
      modifications, without redistributing it, nor anyone redistributing
      BIND without changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those wishing to discuss license compliance may contact ISC at
      <link
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
	https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.13 is an unstable development branch. When its development
      is complete, it will be renamed to BIND 9.14, which will be a
      stable branch.
    </para>
    <para>
      The end of life date for BIND 9.14 has not yet been determined.
      For those needing long term support, the current Extended Support
      Version (ESV) is BIND 9.11, which will be supported until at
      least December 2021. See
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
      for details of ISC's software support policy.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
