<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014-2018  Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
 - purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
 - copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.
 -
 - THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND ISC DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH
 - REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
 - AND FITNESS.  IN NO EVENT SHALL ISC BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT,
 - INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM
 - LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE
 - OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR
 - PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      This document summarizes changes since the last production
      release on the BIND 9.10 branch.
      Please see the <filename>CHANGES</filename> file for a further
      list of bug fixes and other changes.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="root_key"><info><title>New DNSSEC Root Key</title></info>
    <para>
      ICANN is in the process of introducing a new Key Signing Key (KSK) for
      the global root zone. BIND has multiple methods for managing DNSSEC
      trust anchors, with somewhat different behaviors. If the root
      key is configured using the <command>managed-keys</command>
      statement, or if the pre-configured root key is enabled by using
      <command>dnssec-validation auto</command>, then BIND can keep keys up
      to date automatically. Servers configured in this way should have
      begun the process of rolling to the new key when it was published in
      the root zone in July 2017. However, keys configured using the
      <command>trusted-keys</command> statement are not automatically
      maintained. If your server is performing DNSSEC validation and is
      configured using <command>trusted-keys</command>, you are advised to
      change your configuration before the root zone begins signing with
      the new KSK. This is currently scheduled for October 11, 2017.
    </para>
    <para>
      This release includes an updated version of the
      <filename>bind.keys</filename> file containing the new root
      key. This file can also be downloaded from
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/bind-keys">
	https://www.isc.org/bind-keys
      </link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="win_support"><info><title>Legacy Windows No Longer Supported</title></info>
    <para>
      As of BIND 9.10.6, Windows XP and Windows 2003 are no longer supported
      platforms for BIND; "XP" binaries are no longer available for download
      from ISC.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  An error in TSIG handling could permit unauthorized zone
	  transfers or zone updates. These flaws are disclosed in
	  CVE-2017-3142 and CVE-2017-3143. [RT #45383]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The BIND installer on Windows used an unquoted service path,
	  which can enable privilege escalation. This flaw is disclosed
	  in CVE-2017-3141. [RT #45229]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  With certain RPZ configurations, a response with TTL 0
	  could cause <command>named</command> to go into an infinite
	  query loop. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2017-3140.
	  [RT #45181]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Addresses could be referenced after being freed during resolver
	  processing, causing an assertion failure. The chances of this
	  happening were remote, but the introduction of a delay in
	  resolution increased them. This bug is disclosed in
	  CVE-2017-3145. [RT #46839]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  update-policy rules that otherwise ignore the name field now
	  require that it be set to "." to ensure that any type list
	  present is properly interpreted.  If the name field was omitted
	  from the rule declaration and a type list was present it wouldn't
	  be interpreted as expected.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The ISC DNSSEC Lookaside Validation (DLV) service has
	  been shut down; all DLV records in the dlv.isc.org zone
	  have been removed.  References to the service have been
	  removed from BIND documentation.  Lookaside validation
	  is no longer used by default by <command>delv</command>.
	  The DLV key has been removed from <filename>bind.keys</filename>.
	  Setting <command>dnssec-lookaside</command> to
	  <command>auto</command> or to use dlv.isc.org as a trust
	  anchor results in a warning being issued.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> will now log a warning if the old
	  root DNSSEC key is explicitly configured and has not been updated.
	  [RT #43670]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="proto_changes"><info><title>Protocol Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BIND can now use the Ed25519 and Ed448 Edwards Curve DNSSEC
	  signing algorithms described in RFC 8080. Note, however, that
	  these algorithms must be supported in OpenSSL;
	  currently they are only available in the development branch
	  of OpenSSL at
	  <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	    xlink:href="https://github.com/openssl/openssl">
	    https://github.com/openssl/openssl</link>.
	  [RT #44696]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When parsing DNS messages, EDNS KEY TAG options are checked
	  for correctness. When printing messages (for example, in
	  <command>dig</command>), EDNS KEY TAG options are printed
	  in readable format.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> will no longer start or accept
	  reconfiguration if <command>managed-keys</command> or
	  <command>dnssec-validation auto</command> are in use and
	  the managed-keys directory (specified by
	  <command>managed-keys-directory</command>, and defaulting
	  to the working directory if not specified),
	  is not writable by the effective user ID. [RT #46077]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Previously, <command>update-policy local;</command> accepted
	  updates from any source so long as they were signed by the
	  locally-generated session key. This has been further restricted;
	  updates are now only accepted from locally configured addresses.
	  [RT #45492]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +ednsopt</command> now accepts the names
	  for EDNS options in addition to numeric values. For example,
	  an EDNS Client-Subnet option could be sent using
	  <command>dig +ednsopt=ecs:...</command>. Thanks to
	  John Worley of Secure64 for the contribution. [RT #44461]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Threads in <command>named</command> are now set to human-readable
	  names to assist debugging on operating systems that support that.
	  Threads will have names such as "isc-timer", "isc-sockmgr",
	  "isc-worker0001", and so on. This will affect the reporting of
	  subsidiary thread names in <command>ps</command> and
	  <command>top</command>, but not the main thread. [RT #43234]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  DiG now warns about .local queries which are reserved for
	  Multicast DNS. [RT #44783]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Attempting to validate improperly unsigned CNAME responses
	  from secure zones could cause a validator loop. This caused
	  a delay in returning SERVFAIL and also increased the chances
	  of encountering the crash bug described in CVE-2017-3145.
	  [RT #46839]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When <command>named</command> was reconfigured, failure of some
	  zones to load correctly could leave the system in an inconsistent
	  state; while generally harmless, this could lead to a crash later
	  when using <command>rndc addzone</command>.  Reconfiguration changes
	  are now fully rolled back in the event of failure. [RT #45841]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Fixed a bug that was introduced in an earlier development
	  release which caused multi-packet AXFR and IXFR messages to fail
	  validation if not all packets contained TSIG records; this
	  caused interoperability problems with some other DNS
	  implementations. [RT #45509]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Semicolons are no longer escaped when printing CAA and
	  URI records.  This may break applications that depend on the
	  presence of the backslash before the semicolon. [RT #45216]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  AD could be set on truncated answer with no records present
	  in the answer and authority sections. [RT #45140]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Some header files included &lt;isc/util.h&gt; incorrectly as
	  it pollutes with namespace with non ISC_ macros and this should
	  only be done by explicitly including &lt;isc/util.h&gt;.  This
	  has been corrected.  Some code may depend on &lt;isc/util.h&gt;
	  being implicitly included via other header files.  Such
	  code should explicitly include &lt;isc/util.h&gt;.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Zones created with <command>rndc addzone</command> could
	  temporarily fail to inherit the <command>allow-transfer</command>
	  ACL set in the <command>options</command> section of
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [RT #46603]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> failed to properly determine whether
	  there were active KSK and ZSK keys for an algorithm when
	  <command>update-check-ksk</command> was true (which is the
	  default setting). This could leave records unsigned
	  when rolling keys. [RT #46743] [RT #46754] [RT #46774]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      The end of life for BIND 9.10 is yet to be determined but
      will not be before BIND 9.12.0 has been released for 6 months.
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
